Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *Daf* is דף *Daf* ע
*Ayin* 70 and we pick up at the top and we're dealing
with we continue to deal with cases about when do you have
to be concerned issues about supervision and when do you have to
be concerned that the non-Jew might touch the wine or swap it
for other wine or so or similar.
So now we pick up with three lines from the top of
דף *Daf* ע *Ayin*. ההוא ביתא דהוה יתיב ביה חמרא hahu beita
d'hava yativ bei chamra. דישראל *Hahu bayta dehava yasiv bei chamara deyisrael*.
There was a house that had wine owned by a Jew in
it. על עובד כוכבים אחד לדושא באפיה *Al oved kochavim achtal dasha
be'apeih*. Non-Jew came in and locked the door. You remember
one of the concerns of leaving the non-Jew in the store was
even if you didn't tell him when you're coming back maybe he'll
lock the door. But the assumption would be presumably that if he
would lock the door that would raise
concerns as long as he hasn't locked the door you're
okay maybe. Anyway here we have a case where he did lock
the door so maybe we דוקא *davka* should be concerned that he
went ahead and he touched the wine or he did something with
the wine.
So על עובד כוכבים אחד לדושא באפיה *Al oved kochavim achtal dasha
be'apeih*. He locked the door he closed the door in the face
of the Jew. והוי ביזא בדשא *Vahava biza bedasha*. But there was
a crack in the door. אשתכח עובד כוכבים דקאי ביני דני *Ishtakach
oved kochavim dekai beini danei*. And once they got in they found
that the non-Jew was there amongst the barrels. אמר רבא amar Rava,
*Amar Rava* said רבא Rava *Rava* כל דלהדי ביזא שרי *Kol delehadi
biza shari*. Anything any barrels that are opposite the crack that you
could look into the crack and see are okay. Presumably that means
even if you didn't look into the crack but presumably it means
he knew of the crack and therefore he would have avoided manipulating
them. That's what I'm guessing. דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא אסור assur, *Dehai
gisa u'dehai gisa assur* but on either side of the crack where
you didn't have a line of sight אסור *assur* is forbidden. Okay
so basically it means he locked the door you do have to
be concerned what was he doing there behind the locked door right
and therefore it's an issue.
One wonders what would be the story if he wasn't found among
the barrels. Let's say he locked the door and then by the
time you got in you found him I don't know raiding your
fridge or watching TV you know. So how much is being found
among the barrels part of what makes it a problem or is
the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* even though he's found among the barrels anything
that's opposite the crack in the door's okay. All right so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues similar types of stories. ההוא חמרא דישראל
דהוה יתיב בביתא דהוי דייר ישראל Yisrael. בעליונה ועובד כוכבים בתחתונה *Hahu
chamara deyisrael dehava yasiv beveita dehava dayer Yisrael be'ilyona ve'oved kochavim betachtona*.
There was wine owned by a Jew that was in a house
and the Jew was in the top story of the house and
the non-Jew in the bottom story and the way רש״י Rashi *Rashi*
tells it the wine was actually in the bottom story but since
the Jew could at any time you know I don't know maybe
there was like a balcony or something like
that you know he could look down and see it that meant
that the wine would always be okay because the non-Jew would always
be afraid that the Jew might be checking in. Okay that's the
normal case. But then what happened? שמעו קול תיגרא *Shamu kol tigra*.
They heard the sound of some fighting outside so they ran out
to see what was going on. נפיק *Nafik*. They went out. Now
after whatever that fracas resolved itself קדים אתא עובד כוכבים אכטל לדושא
באפיה *Kadim ata oved kochavim achtal dasha be'apeih*. The non-Jew went back
into the home and he went in you know quickly and he
locked the door. So now he's alone with the wine behind a
locked door. Do we have to say that the wine is a
problem?
So אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava* said רבא Rava *Rava* חמר
שרי *Chamar shari* the wine's permissible. מימר אמר meymar amar *Meimar amar*
because the non-Jew presumably will think to himself כי היכי דקדים אתאי
אנא *Ki heichi dekadim ata'i ana* the same way I quickly went
back into the home therefore קדים ואתא ישראל Yisrael. ויתיב בעליונה *Kadim
ve'ata Yisrael veyasiv be'ilyona*
maybe my Jewish you know roommate or whatever the you know housemate
also you know ran back in after the fight and for I
know he's back up in his in you know in on in
his story of the house. So therefore since there's a reasonable reason
I mean again you know one always wonders what if the case
is different what if he sees that the Jew went to get
the police or some you know whatever the case might be. But
anyway but even though the point is similar to the issue of
the crack that even if in reality nobody was looking into the
crack and even if in reality the Jew didn't go in if
it's reasonable that the non-Jew would have you know could have you
know would have reasonably thought hey just because I think I got
in first doesn't mean I did doesn't mean the Jew isn't there
as well that's enough to say that he would be concerned and
not handle the wine ויתיב בעליונה וקחזי לי *Veyasiv be'ilyona vekachazi li*
and he's maybe still sitting up there and observing me. Okay third
case. ההוא אושפיזא דהוה יתיב ביה חמרא דישראל *Hahu ushpiza dehava yasiv
bei chamara deyisrael*. There was an inn that wine owned by a
Jew was in the inn. Okay. אשתכח עובד כוכבים דהוה יתיב ביני
דני *Ishtakach oved kochavim dehava yasiv beini danei*. And there was the
non-Jew was there amongst the barrels so a straight case the door
wasn't locked and so on. So what's the story?
So presumably now so רבא Rava *Rava* says אמר רבא Rava *Amar
Rava* said רבא Rava *Rava* אם נתפס עליו כגנב nitpas alav k'ganav.
שרי *Im nitpas alav kegannav shari*. If he would have been discovered
and had he been discovered sort of stealing the wine,
then it's permissible. If
he would have been discovered mishandling the wine, if that would have
meant that there would have been consequences, then the wine is permissible.
Then you could say that his concern that he'll be discovered is
enough to keep him off. But if were he to be discovered,
I don't know, stealing the wine, a, maybe רש"י Rashi says, you
know, an earlier רש"י Rashi says, maybe he's got an in with
the government and people would look the other way, in, in, haha,
he's guy's an innkeeper whatever. Anyway, you know, this is a powerful
person or whatever and even if he's found manipulating Jewish wine, they
just say, eh, it's the Jews, whatever, you know, they would turn
the other cheek. Or, you know, or let's say he has some
reasonable excuse: oh no, I was just checking to make sure the
wine hadn't gone back, or da da da da da. Anyway, if
there's a way he would get away with it even if he
was discovered handling the wine, then the wine is forbidden. Then you
have to assume that he did handle the wine and he figured
he could get away with it. Okay, but if, had he, were
he not to be discovered amongst the barrels, were he to be
discovered actually going and accessing the wine itself, he would get in
trouble, then even though he was among the barrels, you have to
assume it's all okay. You're allowed to assume it's all okay, which
is, you know, pretty funny because we all know that there are
people that all the time are stealing things or whatever and they
would get in trouble if they were discovered, but they're desperate, you
know, for food, they're hungry, whatever they might be. Okay, but nevertheless,
this is sort of the principle that we're going to use, which
is, is that even though it's a case where maybe he's not
afraid, you know, it gets back to sort of the cases of
our משנה, Mishnah, right? Remember the cases of our משנה Mishnah that
if you don't know that the Jew's away for a long time,
then it's okay because he's afraid the Jew will pop back in?
So that idea of being afraid that the Jew will pop back
in is here being sort of clarified, described as if he were
discovered, he would get in trouble. Okay, so even though it's in
the inn and maybe he's also staying in the inn and he
has a right to be in this room or whatever, nevertheless, and
then you come back and you find him amongst the barrels, you
are allowed to assume it's okay because if he's concerned that people
could drop in at any time and there's a reasonable reason to
be concerned that if he was discovered he'd get in trouble, then
it's considered to be okay. So that's the important principle of נתפס
עליו כגנב. nitpas alav k'ganav Okay, so now we're going to keep
on with similar cases. Let's take a look.
Okay, so, so that in a way really is just an illustration
of the משנה: Mishnah: afraid to get caught, afraid somebody might drop
in and then you'll get caught and you'll get be in trouble.
So now the גמרא Gemara, says like this: אגנבא כומתא דגנבא בער.
aganuva kumta d'ganuva bayar. The hat burns on the head of the
גנב. ganav. Okay, always aware of, okay.
ההוא ביתא דהוה יתיב ביה חמרא. Now there was a house that
had some wine in it. אשתכח עובד כוכבים דהוה קאי ביני דני,
ishtacach oved kochavim d'hava kai bei dane,
and now you found the non-Jew amongst the barrels. I guess part
of the reason this is a
חידוש chiddush added to the משנה Mishnah is that he actually was
there right between the barrels. Okay, and even so, נתפס עליו כגנב
nitpas alav k'ganav. means it's okay. אמר רבא, אי אית ליה לאשתמוטי,
Amar Rava, ei it lei l'ishtamutei, חמרא אסיר. chamra asir.
If he has an excuse what he's doing in the house, the
wine is forbidden. ואי לא חמרא שרי. v'i lo chamra shari. And
if not, the wine is permissible. Now רש"י Rashi says it sounds
very similar to the previous case, but רש"י Rashi, says אית ליה
לאשתמוטי it lei l'ishtamutei is different than נתפס עליו כגנב. nitpas alav
k'ganav? אית ליה לאשתמוטי it lei l'ishtamutei is an excuse what are
you doing here in this house altogether? Why are you in this
room where my wine is being kept, even if you weren't handling
the actual wine itself? So here's the question, okay, which is why
if, let's say he's got an excuse why he's in that room,
okay, no, I was in this room because I thought I don't
know who knows I thought I heard a mouse, I was in
this room because I needed it to get access to the bathroom,
the bathroom's on the other side of the room or something like
that? Then רבא Rava says that it would be forbidden. Now the
question is why is it forbidden? Maybe it's still a case of
נתפס עליו כגנב? nitpas alav keganiv. Okay, again רש"י, Rashi it's not
clear in the גמרא, Gemara but I want to make this clear:
there's two stages, right? One
is... That's
where he is, and he actually is sticking his hand into the
barrel, okay? And then the question there is, right, the question with
that is, you know,
why—not why are you, but, you know,
you're taking
my
wine. And then it's the question of נתפס כגנב. nitpas keganiv. Will
he get in trouble for taking the wine or not? Is he
a type of person that will get in trouble and maybe he
even has an excuse why he's actually taking the wine? Okay, so
normally we say that if you're נתפס כגנב, nitpas keganiv, you're going
to be okay, okay? Here, though, the—here, though, Rashi—the Gemara says that
if the question is, what are you doing there? So if he
has an excuse why he's there, okay, it's going to
be—the wine is going to be no good. If it's אית ליה
אישתמוטי, is lei ishtamutei, then the wine is no good. So Rashi
asks a question. Rashi says, I don't understand, even if he doesn't
have an excuse why he's there, why is the wine no good?
If he would be in a case where he would be נתפס
כגנב, nitpas keganiv, the wine should be good, right? You sort of
see? One question is, why are you there? If you don't have
a good excuse why you're there, then the wine is no good.
Why is that true? Normally we say that as long as you
would get in trouble if you actually were caught stealing the wine,
you'd be okay. So the difference Rashi says is, is that here,
this case is a case where you have a right to be
in the room. All the cases until now were cases where I
left a non-Jew in my store, the non-Jew shares my—you know, we're
in the same inn, we're in the same building together, all those
types of cases. If he's got a right to be there, okay,
then as long as he'll get in trouble if he sticks his
hand in—until that point everything he's doing is okay. So you just,
the basic rule is you don't want to get in trouble. So
in this case, he's totally okay and if he'll get in trouble
by sticking his hand in, then I know that the wine will
be good. But here, he has no right to be in this
room to begin with, and if he—and if he has no good
excuse why he's in this room and he's still willing to be
in this room, then that means he's already willing to get into
trouble. Okay? And since he's already—I mean, maybe that's the easiest way
to say this. As long as he's in a position where he's
willing to get into trouble, okay, then the wine is no good.
Once he's willing to get into trouble, you have to be afraid
you don't know what he did. So if he had a right
to be in the room, okay, as long as he'll get in
trouble if he sticks his hand in the barrel of wine and
there's nothing he's done that shows that he's prepared to get into
trouble, then the wine remains good. But if he has no right
to be in the room and he has no excuse why he's
in the room and he's still in the room, okay, then as
long—then he shows that he's willing to get into trouble. So since
he's shown that he's willing to get into trouble, the wine is
no good. I don't know if I made—was that pretty clear? All
right. So אית ליה אישתמוטי is lei ishtamutei is different than נתפס
עליו כגנב. nitpas alav k’ganav. The bottom line is that if he's—if
he's shown that he's willing to get into trouble, okay, the wine
is no good. So now the Gemara says like this. אמר רבא
אית ליה אישתמוטי חמרא אסור ואי לא חמרא שרי, Amar Rava is
lei ishtamutei chamra assur vei lo chamra shari, if not it's permissible.
So מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you: הניחו בפונדק או שסמכו לשומר אסור.
Hiniho bepundak o shesamcho lishomer assur. You left a non-Jew with the—with
your store and you locked the store and maybe I don't know
you gave him the keys. What? פונדק Pundak is an inn. Thank
you, right, okay. Thank you, sorry. You know, and you locked the
inn but maybe you gave him the keys or you said, hey,
I'm leaving, stay outside and make sure nobody goes in, okay, and
there's wine inside. So he's sort of left alone but he doesn't
have a right to go inside. In that case, it's forbidden. Okay,
so why is it forbidden?
You know, so מאי לאו, mai lav, doesn't it mean אף על
גב דלית ליה אישתמוטי, af al gav deleis lei ishtamutei, even if
he has—'cause even though he has no excuse why he is, you
know, why he would—and presumably then you found him among the wine,
that part is missing. So why is it forbidden? Aren't we talking
about a case where he has no excuse to be inside and
nevertheless the wine—מאי לאו
אף על גב דלית ליה אישתמוטי? mai lav af al gav deleis
lei ishtamutei? He has no—wait a minute, did I get—hold on.
Right, he has no
excuse—now I'm so totally confused. Hold on. I think I got—wait a
minute, I gotta get the אית ליה אישתמוטי. is lei ishtamutei.
Right, so don't you see it is
stricter—wait a minute, I'm sorry, I got this confused. Hold on. Let
me try this again. Oy, hold on a minute.
Yeah, I think I said it wrong a minute ago. I'm sorry,
hold on a minute.
Yeah, I said it wrong a minute ago. Although maybe what I
said made sense. I have to figure out why what I said
didn't make sense, but I said it wrong. Okay? רבא Rava said,
okay, I think I said it the reverse. I
apologize. רבא Rava said if he has an excuse why he's here,
if he can get so he shouldn't be here, but if he
has a way to excuse it, then the wine is forbidden. Then
you figure he's up to no good, he's got a cover story
and the wine is forbidden if he has an excuse, not a
good reason, if he has an excuse, if he has a way
to, you know, to get so if he has a cover story
then the wine is forbidden. Ironically, if he has no excuse why
he's here, so if he has no excuse why he's here, you
would think that it's a bigger problem, right, if you actually found
him? That's why I got it reversed. I mean, maybe if he
didn't go in and he has no excuse, you can assume he
didn't go in. But if he actually did go in and he
has no excuse, then you would think you have to have more
of a suspicion, which is why I got it reversed. What was
the case? That he was found among the wine or not among
the wine? Let's take a look, one minute.
Yeah, he was found among the wine, so I don't know,
that's why I got it reversed, because it's a little bizarre. So
let's read it again though. I apologize, let's read it again. Okay,
ההוא בי סדנא דיתיב ביה חמרא ואשתכח עובד כוכבים וקאי בי דני.
Hahu bei sadna deyativ beih chamra ve-ishtachach oved kochavim veka'ei bei danne.
So he's with the wine. אמר רבא Rava אי אית ליה לאשתמוטי,
i it lei l'ishtamutei,
if he has an excuse, then חמרא אסור, chamra assur, the wine
is forbidden because then you figure he's up to no good and
he's got his cover story and that's why the wine is forbidden
and he shouldn't be in this room to begin with. ואי לא,
ve-ei lo, and if he doesn't have an excuse, then חמרא שרי,
chamra sharei, it's permissible. I think, oh, now remembering, רש"י Rashi says
if he's got an excuse, he feels he can be in this
room and spend all the time he needs because he always has
an excuse. If he doesn't have an excuse, he's only here very
briefly. But it might be he's only here very briefly, but if
he doesn't have an excuse you should all the more reason be
concerned that he's up to no good. So it's very strange. Okay,
if he's here without an excuse, you have to assume he did
not have the leisure of taking his time, he needs to come
in and come out quickly because he'll get in trouble. It's very
bizarre. But if he's got an excuse, that's when you're afraid he's
up to no good. Okay, so let's take a look. מיתיבי, Meitivei,
ננעל הפונדק, Nin'al hapundak, if the store was locked, או שאמר לו
שמור, o she-amar lo shemor, אסור, it's forbidden, and presumably if then
you found him among the wine. מאי לאו אע"ג דלית ליה לאשתמוטי?
Mai lav af al gav deleit lei l'ishtamutei? Aren't we talking about
a case where he doesn't have an excuse? And even so the
wine is forbidden? Even though he doesn't have an excuse and presumably
he won't tarry? לא בדית ליה לאשתמוטי. Lo, bede'it lei l'ishtamutei.
No, it's when he has an excuse, and therefore you're afraid that
he's going to tarry. So again it's quite ironic, when he has
an excuse, he's got a reason and explanation why he's there, the
wine is more forbidden. Okay, let's take the next case. ההוא ישראל
ועובד כוכבים דהוו יתבי וקא שתיין חמרא, Hahu Yisrael ve-oved kochavim de-hava
yatevei ve-ka shatyan chamra, a Jew and a non-Jew were sitting and
drinking wine. Presumably they were drinking each one their own wine. שמע
ישראל קול צלויי בבי כנישתא, Shema Yisrael kol tzeluyei bei kenishta, the
Jew heard them that they were דאוונען davening in the שול. shul.
So he said, oh it's מנחה Mincha time. קם ואזל, Kam ve-azal,
he got up and he left and he left the non-Jew behind
with the wine. And there's wine on the table, Jewish wine on
the table. אמר רבא חמרא שרי, Amar Rava, chamra sharei, the wine
is permissible. מימר אמר השתא מדכר להו לחמרא והדר אתי. Meimar amar,
hashta midkar lehu lechamra ve-hadar atei. He says, yeah my fellow Jew,
he's my friend the Jew there, he's not so פרום, frum, he's
going to remember he left wine
here and he left me alone with the wine, he's going to
leave in the middle of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh to come back
and check on the wine. So because of that, it's like the
case in the משנה Mishna where you didn't tell him how long
you were going. It's a great case, right? If you say, oh
I got to run to מנחה, Mincha, is that like you told
him you were going to be away for a while and he
feels that he's got the license to do what he wants? And
the גמרא's Gemara answer is no, he feels that you're not going
to stay too long at דאוונען davening and you're going to come
back to check in on him and therefore he doesn't do what
he wants.
Okay, so that's why it remains permissible. Okay, ההוא ישראל ועובד כוכבים
דהוו יתבי בארבא, Hahu Yisrael ve-oved kochavim de-hava yatevei be-arba,
they were sitting in a boat. שמע ישראל קול שיפורי דבי שמשי,
Shema Yisrael kol shipurei de-bei shimshi, then he heard the sound of
the שופר shofar at evening time. רש"י Rashi, says, not here but
elsewhere, that the standard use of the word בין השמשות bein hashmashot
means ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, it's about to be nightfall for שבת.
Shabbos. And they blew a שופר shofar blast to know that שבת
Shabbos was about to start, like they do now in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
נפק ואזל, Nafak ve-azal, so he left, he went to get ready
for שבת. Shabbos. So now the non-Jew should feel, hey I'm safe,
this guy's got to
get dressed, go to שול, shul, make his שבת Shabbos meal, I
got a lot of time now all alone with the wine. So
אמר רבא, so רבא said, חמרא שרי, chamra sharei,
the wine is permissible. Why? מימר אמר השתא מדכר ליה לחמרא והדר
אתי, Meimar amar hashta midkar lei l'chamra vehadar atei,
because he'll say to himself, no the Jew's going to remember he
left me with all this wine, he's not going to trust me
with this wine and he'll come back and check up on me.
ואי משום שבתא? Ve-ei mishum Shabta? But one minute, why doesn't he
say to himself, look it's שבת, Shabbos, I got the guy's got
to go have שבת Shabbos meal with his family or whatever, maybe
he's not even allowed to come on the boat on שבת, Shabbos,
he's not allowed to travel back here on שבת. Shabbos. totally safe.
Why doesn't he say that? האמר רבא אמר לי איסור גיורא Ha'amar
Rava amar lee Issur Giyora so רבא said no, איסור גיורא, Issur
Giyora, איסור Issur the גר, Ger, said to me, הוינן בארמיותן Havinan
b'armiutan when I was still a non-Jew, אמרינן amrinan we used to
say, יודאי לא מנטרי שבתא Yudai lo mantri Shabta Jews don't really
keep שבת. Shabbos. Why? דאי מנטרי שבתא dai mantri Shabta because if
they really keep שבת, Shabbos, כמה כיסי משתכחי בשוקא kama kissay mishtakchay
b'shuka we would find a lot of wallets in the
marketplace because we see that they're in the marketplace till a minute
before שבת Shabbos and then when it gets dark, if they were
really serious about it, they would drop their wallets and they would
leave. Obviously the sort of subtext here is it's not they don't
keep it at all, but when it comes to protecting their money,
they don't keep
it. Those old canards, those old sort of perceptions about Jews and
money, whatever, it's not being said explicitly here but I think that's
implicit. When it comes to protecting keeping their wallets on them or
protecting their money, they're not so careful about שבת Shabbos and therefore
the same is true by the wine. He knows that the Jew
left to go keep שבת, Shabbos, but he also knows that the
Jew left all these barrels of wine with me.
The non-Jew assumes that when it comes to money, the Jews aren't
going to be so careful about שבת Shabbos and that's good here
because it means that the wine is permissible because he's always afraid
the Jew will come back and check up on the wine.
Now there's a subtext here that we'll know if this is his
friend that he's drinking with, the friend isn't going to go out
of his way to ruin the guy's wine, but they can't say
that?
I don't know, that's a good question. I don't know if in
any of these stories, in this story when they're sitting and drinking
wine together you assume that they're friends or at least friendly, but
all these stories are mostly done to explain how the wine still
remains permissible without them specifically being about the case of friends, there's
all these other cases where it's not that. So I don't know.
But this does seem so
far-fetched that they really think that their guy's Jew's going to come
back during שבת. Shabbos. But that's what the גמרא Gemara seems to
be claiming. To me it's more the opposite, these
Jewish stereotypes about Jews. כמה כיסי משתכחי בשוקא kama kissay mishtakchay b'shuka
ולא ידענא או אינהו לא ידעי v'lo yadana o inhu lo yadi
and I said context if this is still איסור גיורא Issur Giyora
speaking or the גמרא Gemara speaking. I at that time wasn't aware
that the reason the Jews don't leave their wallets in the marketplace
on שבת, Shabbos, דסבירא לן dsavira lan that we hold כרבי יצחק
k'Rabbi Yitzchak דאמר רבי יצחק da'amar Rabbi Yitzchak המוצא כיס בשבת hamotzi
kiss b'Shabbos מוליכו פחות פחות מארבע אמות molicho pachos pachos m'arba amos
that the rabbis actually gave a way that you wouldn't be caught
with your wallet on שבת Shabbos and have to drop it in
the middle of the marketplace.
That you can slowly walk less than four אמות. amos. I don't
know how you deal with the מוקצה muktzeh issue either, maybe it's
already on you. So if it's already in your pocket, you're not
directly manipulating it in terms of the מוקצה muktzeh issue. Anyway, they
gave a special allowance. ודווקא v'davka the reason the rabbis gave this
special allowance that you could do it slowly move it
without
technically carrying it, each sort of advance is less than four אמות
amos was specifically the irony is why do the rabbis allow it?
Normally they don't let you carry things in this tricky way, multiple
steps less than four אמות. amos. And the reason is that they
knew that if they didn't allow you, you would break שבת Shabbos
because you'd be concerned about your money. So in a way it's
actually true, we are concerned that Jews will break שבת Shabbos if
it's an issue of their money, so we had to find a
way to allow it. But now technically they're not breaking שבת. Shabbos.
But because the non-Jews have some perception of this reality about our
anxiety around our money and dealing with the challenges of that on
שבת, Shabbos, the wine remains okay. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ההוא אריה hahu arya there was a lion דהוה
נהים במעצרתא d'hava nahim b'matzarta that was roaring in the
winepress. שמע עובד כוכבים shama oved kochavim so the non-Jew heard, טשא
ביני דני tasha bayni danay and he went to where the barrels
were and he hid among the barrels. Do we have to be
afraid that while he's hiding among the barrels he's drinking some wine
or to calm his nerves or he's doing some ניסוך? nisuch? אמר
רבא חמר שרי amar Rava chamar shari the wine is permissible. מימר
אמר כי היכי דטשינא אנא kee haychee d'tashina ana איטשו נמי ישראלי
אחרי itshu nami Yisraeli achorai the same way I'm hiding in the
barrels, the Jews are hiding in the barrels from this wine, וחזו
לי v'chazu lee and they'll be watching me.
הנך גנבי hanach ganvay so all these different ways in which even
though the non-Jew is among the barrels you don't have to be
afraid that he manipulated the wine. הנך גנבי
דסלקי לפומבדיתא hanach ganvay d'salki l'Pumbedita there was some גנבים ganavim that
came to פומבדיתא Pumbedita ופתחו חביתא טובא ufitchu chavita tuva and they
opened up a lot of barrels of wine to drink the wine
or to whatever they were doing. אמר רבא חמר שרי amar Rava
chamar shari the wine is permissible.
מאי טעמא mai tama רובא גנבי ישראל נינהו ruba ganvay Yisrael ninhu
most גנבים ganavim are ישראל. Don't let this line out. We always
are concerned about the fact that the גמרא Gemara has all these
negative stereotypes about non-Jews and a lot of that was in our
מסכת, masechet, so now we've got number one a stereotype that Jews
will break שבת Shabbos for money and now we've got a line
that most גנבים ganavim are ישראל. Of course that's a little bizarre
because the Jews are a tiny percentage of the world population. So
if you look at the side it says פירוש peirush that רבא
was talking about where he lived in מחוזא Mechuza דשם היו דרים
רק מעט עובדי כוכבים d'sham hayu darim rak m'at ovday kochavim in
מחוזא Mechuza the majority of people... The majority of people in מחוזא
Mechuza were Jews and therefore what רבא is saying is,
oh that's lovely, and what רבא is saying is that here in
מחוזא Mechuza don't assume, oh, the non-Jews are going to be גנבים.
ganavim. No, the majority of the population is Jewish and the majority
of the גנבים ganavim are also going to be Jewish. Okay, and
therefore you can assume that these גנבים ganavim were Jewish and they
were the ones that handled the wine. רבא didn't get along so
well with the people of מחוזא Mechuza in general. Okay, willing to
call them גנבים ganavim or anyway certainly say that if there's גנבים
ganavim it's most likely here that they're Jews. Okay, so let's take
a look. הוי עובדא בנהרדעא. Havu uvda be-Naharda. Now there was a
story in נהרדעא. Naharda. נהרדעא Naharda it's not true that the majority
are Jewish. The majority are non-Jewish. ואמר שמואל חמר שרי. Ve-amar Shmuel
chamar shari. The wine is permissible even though גנבים ganavim came in
and they opened barrels of wine. Why? כמאן כרבי אליעזר דאמר ספק
ביאה טהור. Ke-man ke-Rabbi Eliezer d'amar safek bi'ah tahor. Is this going
like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that if there's a doubt
if the person entered it's טהור. tahor. What does this mean? This
is about the principle that ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים safek tumah bi-reshut
ha-rabim if you have a doubt if somebody touched something טמא, tamei,
if it's in the public domain it's טהור, tahor, if it's in
a private domain it's טמא. tamei. Okay, now here's the case. תנן,
Tenan, we taught in the משנה. Mishna. הנכנס לבקעה בימות הגשמים. Ha-nichnas
la-bik'ah bi-yemot ha-geshamim. You're going into a בקעה bik'ah during the rainy
season. And in the rainy season a בקעה bik'ah of all these
fields that are planted with wheat is considered to be רשות היחיד
reshut ha-yachid because the owners do not like you trampling on their
fields. A lot of people aren't traveling on the roads in the
rainy season and the owners don't like you trampling on their fields.
So it's רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. Okay, and in one of those
fields a body is buried. We know where the bodies are buried.
Okay, but we don't know where the bodies are buried. So anyway,
so it's a רשות היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, you don't know if you
entered into the field where the body is buried. Should we say
it's a case of ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah bi-reshut ha-yachid
and you're טמא? tamei? So the הלכה halacha is הנכנס לבקעה בימות
הגשמים וטומאה בשדה פלוני ha-nichnas la-bik'ah bi-yemot ha-geshamim ve-tumah be-sadeh ploni and
there's a body buried in a certain field. ואמר הלכתי במקום פלוני.
Ve-amar halachti be-makom peloni. I went into the בקעה. bik'ah. ואיני יודע
אם נכנסתי לאותו שדה. Ve-eini yodeia im nichnasti le-oto sadeh.
It's not like I went into the field and I don't know
if I walked over the body. I don't even know if I
went into the right field where the body was buried. So is
that a case of ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah bi-reshut ha-yachid
or not? So אם לא נכנסתי, im lo nichnasti, if I did
not go. רבי אליעזר אומר ספק ביאה טהור. Rabbi Eliezer omer safek
bi'ah tahor. In that case you're actually טהור tahor because you don't
even know if you went into the region where the body was.
Now the question is how do you define the region, right? What
defines a field? Ownership? So if a person owns a thousand acres,
that is, you know, as opposed to different owners of different things.
So it's not exactly clear how you define it. But he basically
said if you know you're in the region and you don't know
you touched it, that's where we say ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek
tumah bi-reshut ha-yachid is טמא. tamei. But if you don't know if
you entered into the field itself then you're like one degree removed
then you're טהור. tahor. ספק ביאה טהור ספק מגע טמא. Safek bi'ah
tahor, safek maga tamei. So is that so we're saying how is
that comparable here? It's comparable in the following way that you don't
know, why do we say the wine is okay? They opened up
the wine. Maybe they touched it. We should say the possibility that
they touched it is sort of similar the same way by רשות
היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, ספק safek if you touch the טומאה tumah you're
טמא. tamei. ספק safek if a non-Jew... all these cases you don't
know for sure the non-Jew touched the wine. Right, all these cases
is the wine is a problem when there's a possibility he touched
the wine if you can't discount that possibility. So why don't we
say ספק safek he touched the wine? So maybe this is like
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Why? Because maybe it's like a case of
sort of like ספק ביאה. safek bi'ah. You don't even know if
they entered in. Why? They did open the barrels. But okay, if
even if most of the גנבים ganavim are non-Jews, maybe some of
the גנבים ganavim are Jews. So therefore you don't know if a
non-Jew actually opened the barrel. If you know a non-Jew opened the
barrel then it's a case of ספק מגע safek maga and it's
טמא, tamei, you don't know if he touched it. But if you
don't know if a non-Jew even opened the barrel, maybe the barrel
was open from before, maybe a Jewish גנב ganav opened the barrel
and so on, that should be a case of ספק ביאה safek
bi'ah and we should say טהור, tahor, it's okay. So maybe that's
the reason it should be okay. Are we saying that this is
like רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? So the גמרא Gemara, says לא, lo,
not necessarily. שאני התם דכיון דאידחא דפתחי משום ממונא הוו להו ספק
ספיקא. Shani hatam dekivan de-it-cha depatchi mishum mamona havu lehu sefek sefeka.
No, there, even if a non-Jew opened it, it's not a question
of there was a definite ביאה, bi'ah, let's say. The non-Jew, we're
going to assume all the גנבים ganavim are non-Jews. The non-Jew definitely
opened it, so he definitely was present. So why then is it
okay? It's okay because even though he was present there's a ספק
ספיקא sefek sefeka a double doubt. What's the double doubt? The double
doubt is maybe normally, even under normal circumstances you would say maybe
he touched it, maybe he didn't. I mean I'm reading this a
little different than רש"י, Rashi I'll tell you how רש"י Rashi means
it in a minute. Maybe he touched it, maybe he didn't touch
it even though he opened it. But here there's another reason to
say he didn't touch it. Because what, they're גנבים. ganavim. They're not
interested in wine. They're opening barrels to see maybe that's where you
stored your cash. So therefore because their interest is in looking for
money and not... not interested in the wine, that creates a double
doubt. The double doubt is, I mean it's not exactly clear in
the גמרא, Gemara the way I'll say the double doubt is, maybe,
you know, he,
well, I guess this is why רש״י Rashi says because maybe he
touched it, maybe he didn't touch it, and it's actually not a
double doubt because there's just two reasons why he didn't touch it.
Maybe he didn't get around to touching it, you know, maybe he
didn't touch it because he was looking for cash. So רש״י Rashi
actually says the double doubt is what I was sort of saying
before: maybe he was Jewish, maybe he's not Jewish, and even if
you think he's not Jewish, maybe he didn't touch it. Why didn't
he touch it? If it's wine, if he's looking for wine, he
definitely touched it. The reason he didn't touch it is because maybe
he's not looking for wine, he's looking for cash. Okay, so basically
the idea is, is that, is that now the thing is that
תוספות Tosafot says that this is not really that different than the
case of ספק ביאה, Safek Biah, right? Because the case of ספק
ביאה Safek Biah is also essentially a double doubt. If you're all
the fields and there's a body under one of them and this
guy doesn't know which field he went into, okay, it's sort of
like a double doubt. Maybe I went into that field and even
if I
didn't go into, and even if I did go into the field,
maybe I walked over the dead body, maybe I didn't walk over
the dead body. So that essentially is, this is the way תוספות
Tosafot explains, is the way the גמרא Gemara is explaining the ספק
ביאה Safek Biah of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that there's a two
degree, two like degrees removed. Okay, and here by comparable it's a
double doubt. Maybe the person who opened the barrel was Jewish, maybe
not Jewish. Even if he was not Jewish, I don't assume he
definitely touched the wine because he was interested in money, he wasn't
interested in wine. So he saw it was wine and maybe he
moved
on. Okay, alright, so let's take a look. We'll come back to
a case like that in a little bit.
ההיא רביתא דאשתכח בי דני, Hahi ravita de'ishtakhakh be danei, there was
a young girl that was found among the barrels of wine, non-Jewish.
והוה נקיטא אופיא בידה, Vehave nikita ufya biyada, and she had some
wine froth in her hand. So should you assume that meant she
definitely stuck her hand in the barrel to get off the wine
froth? אמר רבא חמר שרי, Amar Rava khamar sharei, the wine's permissible.
אימור מגבא דחביתא שקלתה. Eimor migaba de'khavita shaklata. She probably took it
from the back of the barrel of the wine. She didn't stick
her hand in the barrel, it was on the sides of the
barrel. ואף על גב דליכא תו, Ve'af al gav delika tu, even
though there's no more froth on the sides of the barrel, so
we should assume that it was from in the barrel, not the
sides. No, אימור איצרומי איצרום לה, eimor isrumyei isramila, we should assume
that just by chance that there was just a little froth and
that's what she got on her hands and that's what we'll really
assume rather than assuming she stuck her hand in it. So obviously
some of this is started to get a little suspicious, right? Because
it does sound like really, that's more likely that it was from
the outside, not the inside? So רש״י Rashi also throws in the
fact that she's just a young girl and therefore we don't assume
that even if she's touching wine, she has in her mind to
use it in an עבודה זרה avodah zarah type of a context,
okay? You might remember that from before, there was a discussion of
children who don't yet are not yet aware like know the type
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah context and that makes it more lenient.
Alright, next case.
ההוא פולמוסא, Hahu polmusa, there was a certain troop or רש״י Rashi
says like a general of a troop because the word פולמוס, polmus,
right, is the word like polemic. It means a fight, it means
a war. פולמוס polmus means a war, so פולמוסא polmusa also means
like a general or something, okay? So a troop, a head of
a troop דסליק לנהרדעא, desalik le'Nehardea, came to Nehardea. פתחו חביתא טובא,
Pitchu khavita tuva, they opened up a lot of barrels. We're back
to that. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar,
when this came when רב דימי Rav Dimi said, עובדא הוה קמיה
דרבי אלעזר, uvda hava kamei de'Rabbi Elazar, a case like this just
happened before רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, ושרא, veshara, and he permitted it.
Now why? Why don't we say as opposed to the case before
about גנבים ganavim where we could say there were non-Jewish גנבים, ganavim,
maybe we should presumably assume that the troops are, I mean that
there were Jewish גנבים, ganavim, here we should assume the troops are
non-Jewish. And if they opened the barrels of wine, let's be afraid
that they drank from it. So ולא ידנא, velo yadna, I don't
know why he permitted it. אי משום דסבר לה כרבי אליעזר, Ei
mishum desavar lah ke'Rabbi Eliezer, we're back to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
דאמר ספק ביאה טהור, de'amar safek biah tahor, if it's a doubt
if they entered in, it's טהור. tahor. Now again, it's not clear
what the doubt is that they entered in. It sounds like that
they opened the barrels of wine, okay?
אי משום דסבר רובא דאזלי בהדי פולמוסא ישראל נינהו, Ei mishum desavar
ruba de'azlei bahadi polmusa Yisrael nin-hu, it would be pretty interesting. Most
of the people that go with these troops are Jews, okay? Why
we should assume that, okay? But anyway, but if you assume a
majority of the soldiers are Jews, then you could assume that it
was a Jew who opened the barrel of wine.
אי הכי, Ei hakhi, okay so that's one possibility to say it's
okay is that the majority were Jews, which is a pretty funny
assumption of fact, but if that's true, fine. But if the majority
are not Jews, the גמרא Gemara, now and this hopefully will clarify
a little bit about what we discussed before, if the majority are
not Jews, why do you call it ספק ביאה? safek biah? Before
we called it ספק ביאה, safek biah, remember because there were two
doubts: maybe it was a Jew, maybe it was a non-Jew even
if the majority are non-Jews, and even if it was a non-Jew,
maybe they weren't interested in the wine because they were just interested
in the cash, right? Remember that was the case before why we
considered it to be a double doubt. Okay, but here, if they're
troops, presumably they're not there to steal, they might be there to
confiscate the food because they're hungry, but they're not there to steal.
So if the majority are not Jewish, it's just, you know, it's
like if a non-Jew opened it, he definitely handled the wine. the
wine. What's the issue? So אי הכי ei hachi says the גמרא,
Gemara if that's true, הא ספק ביאה, ha safek biah, what do
you mean it's a doubtful if they entered into the field? Like
it's a double doubt. ספק מגע הוא safek maga hu it's a
single doubt. כיון דמיפתחי טובא keivan demiftachi tuva so no, the answer
is no. If they'd only opened one or two barrels of wine,
I would say it's a single doubt. They're just thirsty and they're
coming to take the wine. And the only doubt is I don't
know maybe it was a Jew who opened it. But because they
opened multiple barrels, כיון דמיפתחי טובא keivan demiftachi tuva because they opened
multiple barrels אימא דאתי בממונא פתחו eima de’atei bemamona pat’chu וכספק ביאה
דמי. u’kesafek biah dami. Even though they're troops and normally I just
assume troops are there to confiscate food, but why are they opening
20 barrels? They don't need 20 barrels. So it looks like they're
also looking for money. And since it looks like they're also looking
for money, I have a reason to say they didn't handle the
wine. Okay, so basically this helps clarify the earlier issue and we're
basically back to is, is that if there's a double doubt, it's
okay. And the double doubt is maybe Jew, maybe non-Jew, and even
if it's a non-Jew, under normal circumstances a non-Jew opens a barrel
of wine, there's no doubt, you assume that they handled the wine.
Why else are they opening it? But in the case that they're
גנבים ganavim or in a case if they're troops and they're opening
a lot of barrels, there's reason to think they're not interested in
the wine. They're interested in looking for cash, and even if they
opened it, maybe they didn't handle it. And since that would be
the case, that's the- you have that double doubt and therefore the
wine is okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara. says like
this.
Did you see how much more lenient? More lenient, whereas before just
catching the guy in the room when there's no evidence that he
even opened it.
That's true. There he's just between the barrels and the barrels aren't
even open. Although in most of those cases we found ways to
be okay, but the- the flip side of the coin was if
he doesn't have an excuse, if he does have an excuse whatever
it's no good even though he's just among the barrels.
It's a good point. You know, maybe part of the issue has
to also be here also is sort of the צרכי רבים tzorchei
rabbim of the idea. They came into a town, right, and now
what? We're going to אסר asser all the wine in the town
or something like that? Like it sounds like, you know, it was
a bigger communal need. But you are right, like the general question
of the thrust is the thrust to find some excuse to say
that it's okay? Because like the case about like the frost or
whatever it's like give me a break, really? Like so you're right,
the whole thrust of these cases is let's find some way to
say it's okay, right? As opposed to some of the other ones
which were a little bit more complicated. But even there I would
say that it seems to be- Well, I guess you're right. The
חידוש here is is that the barrels are open. You know, but
like, yeah, I hear your point. I hear your point.
Also seems like they start with this very principled
חומרא chumra
and then they move to practice.
You're right, that does happen sometimes in the גמרא. Gemara Like while
the גמרא Gemara is dealing with the משנה, Mishnah, it seems to
be very narrow the allowance. And then when it starts dealing with
real cases, you just see this very broad application. Ah, sure, it's
okay for this reason. So it's a good point, like maybe what
we're really looking at is like- is- you know, some historical development
and they just had a need to, you know, to expand the
allowances more expansively. It's a very good point, you're right.
Yeah, because that definitely is the thrust of all of these stories.
Okay, let's see another story. ההיא מוסתא hahi musavisa דמסרה אקלידא. demasla
aklida. So there was a- somebody who was like a Rashi says
a female wine seller, okay, from like the word זולביס סובי, zolvis
sovei, like, okay, and דמסרה אקלידא demasla aklida לעבודת כוכבים. le’avodat kochavim.
She gave the key to the door, to the lock, to the
non-Jew. Okay, and and you know, and and to the wine cabinet.
So now what does she have to suspect about the wine behind
the wine cabinet? I mean maybe somebody said to her: Hi, you're
not allowed to do that. Now he's got access to the wine.
So אמר רב יצחק amar Rav Yitzchak אמר רב אלעזר amar Rav
Elazar עובדא הוה בי מדרשא. uvda hava be midrasha. This case was
brought up in the Beit Midrash. ואמרו v’amru לא מסרה אלא שמירת
מפתח בלבד. lo masrah ella shemirat mofte’ach bilvad.
He was given the job to watch the key. He wasn't given
the right to access the, you know, to access the liquor cabinet.
You know, it's like: Hold on to my key. You're not- your
job is not- I'm not telling you you can access it when
you need to. No, you're just watching the key. So that's again
pretty amazing. There he is, he's holding on to the key and
we're not afraid that he accessed the liquor cabinet. Again, maybe that
would sort of be a case about like נתפס עליו כגנב. nitpas
alav k’ganav. If she came back and said: Hey, what are you
doing opening the cabinet? I didn't tell you to do that. All
right, so even though he's holding on to the key, that- we're
not afraid he accessed the cabinet. אמר אביי amar Abaye
אמר אביי amar Abaye אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanina.
We also thought similarly in a case by טהרות. taharot. Here again,
the interesting thing of comparing סתם יינם stam yeinam to the issue
of טהרה tahara and טומאה tumah touching things. We had it way
back at the- you know, we had it at the beginning of
this about having your workers שלעפ shlep your טהור tahor fruit and
do you have to be afraid that they touched it? So there's
a lot of these comparisons of טומאה tumah ספק safek if you
touched it. Be sure
your עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. The non-Jew doesn't touch the wine. The
whole associations of non-Jews and טומאה tumah also, so there's a lot
of associations here.
Okay, so אביי Abaye said אף אנן נמי תנינא, Af anan nami
tanina, we taught similarly המוסר מפתחות לעם הארץ, Hamossar maftechot l'am ha'aretz,
if you gave over keys to an עם הארץ am ha'aretz of
warehouses that had טהור tahor fruit in it, טהרותיו טהורות, taharotav tahorot,
they're טהור, tahor, you don't have to be afraid that they touched
it. לפי שלא מסר לו אלא שמירת המפתח בלבד, Lefi shelo masar
lo ela shemirat hamafteiach bilvad, their job's just watching the keys, they
don't have right to access it. And so now אביי Abaye says
השתא טהרותיו טהורות, Hashta tahorotav tahorot, if we're going to be so
lenient to allow even from the laws of טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah,
יין נסך מבעיא, yein nesech mibaya, how much more so should we
be lenient by יין נסך? yein nesech? Which is pretty amazing, which
is like what's exactly that hierarchy? He assumes that we, when it
comes to the world of טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, we're greater concerns
and we would be more ready to say it's a problem than
by יין נסך. yein nesech. Is it just that we attach more
stringencies to טומאה וטהרה? tumah v'taharah? Is it that by טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah more people are
טמא? tamei? The עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz outnumber the חברים chaverim or
whatever, and maybe אדרבה adraba because they don't treat it so weightily,
maybe there's more of a likelihood. It doesn't explain why he thinks
that. Is it because of the weight of that area of הלכה,
halacha, is it because of the circumstances and the likelihoods of touching
and so on? But nevertheless, אביי Abaye says we are more
concerned of and more prepared to say that something became טמא tamei
than we are to say it became יין נסך. yein nesech. And
if even so we say when they're watching the keys, we don't
assume the fruit became טמא, tamei, we'll certainly say the same thing
about wine. Okay.
So
the גמרא Gemara says למימרא, lemeimra, does that mean this sounds like
it's saying דטהרות אלימי מיין נסך, d'taharot alimi miyein nesech, that טהרות
taharot are weightier than יין נסך? yein nesech? We're more ready to
identify a problem with טהרות taharot than by wine. אין, In, yes,
that's true דאתמר, d'itmar, because it was taught חצר שחלקה במסיפס, Chatzer
she'chelka be'mispis,
you have, you share a yard with a, and on the other,
and on the neighboring yard is either a non-Jew or a Jew
who's an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. So either it's a concern of
wine or it's going to be a concern about טהרות. taharot. Okay,
and you've got a boundary line, you have some low like bushes
between the yards, okay? So it's not impossible to cross over, but
the guy can't say oh, he accidentally is in your yard and
he didn't realize, because there's a line of bushes or of like
a low fence there or of rocks to demarcate the hedges, to
demarcate the boundary line. שחלקה במסיפס. she'chelka be'mispis. אמר רב Amar Rav
טהרותיו טמאות, taharotav tameiot, if your neighbor is a Jew who's an
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, you have to be afraid, you can't assume
that that boundary line is going to stop him from crossing over.
You're afraid he's going to cross over and he might handle your
fruit and therefore it is טמא. tamei.
ובעובד כוכבים אינו עושה יין נסך, Uve'oveid kochavim eino oseh yein nesech,
but for a non-Jew you don't have to be a concern that
he traveled over and he touched your wine and that the wine
is טמא. tamei. Again, not at all clear what the difference is.
Is it just that one where we just we consider the issue
more serious and more weighty about it? Is it that,
I don't know, is it the circumstances somehow that a non-Jew there's
less likely will handle your wine than your neighbor Jew will touch
your fruit? Anyway, whatever the case might be, רב Rav says in
that case we will say that the we treat the issue of
טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah more weightily and we say your fruit is
טמא, tamei, but the wine is still okay. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר,
Rabbi Yochanan amar, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan treats them equally אף
טהרותיו טהורות. Af taharotav tehorot. No, it's good enough for even for
טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Okay, so it's not clear that he gives
them any different weight, that boundary line is good enough to make
sure that he's not, it's like a נתפס לאו כגנב nitpas l'o
keganiv type of a case, or ליכא לאשתמוטי, leka leishtamotei, whatever the
case might be. Since he has no excuse why he's in your
yard, everything is okay, even for טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah.
מיתבי, Meitvei, I'll ask you on this. And now we're going to
see: is it true that רב's Rav contention that טומאה וטהרה tumah
v'taharah is weightier than יין נסך yein nesech in terms of concerns
of when it was handled? מיתבי Meitvei הפנימית של חבר והחיצונה של
עם הארץ. Hapnimis shel chaver vehachitzona shel am ha'aretz. You've got a
one courtyard behind another courtyard, okay? So you basically have here,
here's
the main thoroughfare, okay? Here's the outer courtyard and then here's the
inner one. Okay, so anybody who lives in the inner courtyard is
always going to travel through the outer one to get to the
main thoroughfare. He's got a right to be in the outer courtyard.
But anybody who lives in the outer courtyard has no right to
be on the inner courtyard. What are you doing in my yard?
Okay. So הפנימית של חבר, Hapnimis shel chaver, the inner courtyard belongs
to the חבר, chaver, the one who's careful for טומאה וטהרה. tumah
v'taharah. והחיצונה
של עם הארץ, Vehachitzona shel am ha'aretz, and the outer one belongs
to the עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. So the עם הארץ am ha'aretz
has no excuse what he's doing in the inner courtyard. אותו חבר
שוטח שם פירות ומניח שם כלים, Oso chaver shetoach sham peirot u'maniach
sham keilim, he can spread out his fruit, the חבר, chaver, and
put his vessels there, his טהור tahor vessels, ואף על פי שידו
של עם הארץ מגשת לשם, ve'af al pi she'yado shel am ha'aretz
mageshet l'sham, even though the עם הארץ am ha'aretz could just stand
in his courtyard and reach his hand over and touch it, and
he could touch the fruit, you're not... Afraid, you think that the
boundary line is enough for טומאה טהרה tumah taharah purposes, okay, even
to keep an עם הארץ am ha'aretz away, because there's a clear
boundary line. So that seems to be a good proof like רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it's good enough even for טומאה טהרה. tumah
taharah. So the גמרא Gemara says, קשיא לרב, kashya l'Rav, that's difficult
to רב Rav because that shows that a boundary line is good
enough even for טומאה טהרה. tumah taharah. אמר לך רב, amar lach
Rav, רב Rav would say to you, שאני התם דנתפס עליו כגנב.
shani hatam d'nitpas alav k’ganav. No, there's that phrase again נתפס עליו
כגנב. nitpas alav k'ganav What the heck are you doing sticking your
hand into my yard? Now the question is how's that different? Somehow
we have to assume that the case of when you've just got
two yards next to each other and a little hedge, okay, you
can it's a little bit different because if they're two yards next
to each other, you can say oops I overstepped, you know, I
don't know, I was playing ball with my kid and I ran
to catch the ball or something like that. But a case of
like front and back as opposed to side-by-side, here to be sticking
your hand in, you have absolutely no excuse. So you'll be extra
careful and there the boundary line is enough. But somehow in the
two fields that are side-by-side, רב Rav says the boundary line is
not enough, you'll have an excuse and that's where I will be
afraid at least for טומאה טהרה. tumah taharah. So there's again that
נתפס עליו כגנב phrase. תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר גגו של חבר למעלה מגגו של עם הארץ.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer gago shel chaver l'ma'ala migago shel am
ha'aretz. They were spreading out their fruit on their rooftops, they had
flat rooftops. And the rooftop of the חבר, chaver, he's on a
higher building than the עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. So for the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz to be able to touch the fruit in the
roof of the חבר, chaver, he'd have to stretch up his hand
and go like this. So there's very little excuse, what's your hand
doing on my rooftop?
Okay, עושה חבר
שטוח שם פירות ומניח שם כלים ובלבד שלא תהא ידו של עם
הארץ מגשת לשם. oseh chaver shoteach sham peirot u’maniach sham keilim u’vilvad
she’lo tehei yado shel am ha’aretz mageshet l’sham. Okay, as long as
the arm of the עם הארץ am ha'aretz can't reach there. But
if the arm of the עם הארץ am ha'aretz could reach there,
it would be a problem. So קשיא לרבי יוחנן, kashya l'Rabbi Yochanan,
that's difficult for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. There it sounds like you've
got a boundary line where he would have no good excuse, right,
what the heck is your hand doing on my rooftop? And nevertheless,
if he's theoretically able to reach it, it's a problem. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said the boundary line is enough to keep the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz out, and here we see the boundary line
is not enough to keep the עם הארץ am ha'aretz out, even
a nice good boundary line like a higher rooftop is not enough
to keep the עם הארץ am ha'aretz out. So that's a challenge
for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So אמר לך רבי יוחנן, amar lach
Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say back to you, שאני
התם דאיתא לאישתמוטי. shani hatam d'isa l'ishtamutei. No, he's got an excuse.
What's his excuse? מימר אמרי אם מצרי קא ממצינא, meimar amri im
mitzrei ka memtzina, I'm measuring, I wanted to see how higher, how
tall your building was, so I was stretching my arm to see
how tall your building was. Or רש"י Rashi says another way of
reading those words, רש"י Rashi, says is, I was just yawning, I
was exercising. It's a little bizarre, okay, it's a pretty weak answer.
Here רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the boundary line is enough, you
don't have an excuse, and therefore I assume my fruit is okay.
But when it's side-by-side and there's just a little hedge. But a
real rooftop like that, there you could have an excuse, I was
measuring the height of your rooftop or something. Anyway, now when you
get down to it, it seems like, you know, it's a lot
of just the circumstances. They all agree there are cases where you
have a good excuse and therefore it's a problem, cases you don't
have a good excuse and therefore it's not a problem, okay, and
the only case they debate is this case, is it a case
that you could get away with stretching your hand and have a
good excuse or not? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. says like
this. תא
שמע, ta shma, come and hear. גגו של חבר בצד גגו של
עם הארץ. gago shel chaver betzad gago shel am ha'aretz. Let's say
they're side-by-side, the rooftop. So that's ממש mamash just like this case,
they're side-by-side. עושה חבר שטוח שם פירות ומניח שם כלים ואף על
פי שידו של עם הארץ מגשת לשם. oseh chaver shoteach sham peirot
u’maniach sham keilim ve’af al pi she’yado shel am ha’aretz mageshet l’sham.
You can put your fruit there even though the guy can reach
it. Okay, so it sounds like we're not afraid he's going to
reach over the boundary line, that sounds like what it's saying.
So קשיא לרב, kashya l'Rav, that's difficult to רב. Rav. רב Rav
said the boundary line is enough to keep him out,
right, so, right, so אמר לך רב, amar lach Rav, so רב
Rav would say to you,
לאו איכא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דקאי כוותי. lav ika Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel d’kai kevasi. האמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, ha’amar Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel, fine, you're right. This case says that the boundary line
is enough. But this case, which is even more extreme of the
rooftops, right, the case of the rooftops here and here's your fruit
and here's the guy, right there רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel said that if you can reach it, it's a problem.
So clearly there's a debate of תנאים. tanna'im. Because here it says
if you can reach it, it's not a problem, and this is
an easier excuse why you have your hand over,
and here it says if you can reach it, it is a
problem. So I go like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is more prepared
to see problems in these cases than the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
and that's what I say. So okay, that was a series of
various cases by טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah whether we say do you
have a legitimate excuse and if you don't have a legitimate and
if you're and, you know, okay and... And if you don't, if
you don't have a legitimate excuse, then we say that the stuff
is okay, we're not afraid you're going to reach your hand over.
But if you might be able to come up with a legitimate
excuse, it's not good. Anyway, those are cases of טומאה וטהרה, Tumah
VeTahara, another set of applications of נתפס כגנב. Nitpas Ke-ganav. And again,
what's interesting is the parallels that we see between concerns of like
we had ספק מגע, Safek Magga, entering into a רשות הרבים, Reshut
Ha-rabbim, ספק ביאה, Safek Bi'ah, did you become טמא, Tamei, did you
know cases of an עם הארץ Am Ha-aretz touching your fruit, a
non-Jew touching your wine? All these types of טומאה וטהרה Tumah VeTahara
getting mixed up with the סתם יינם Stam Yeinam issues. Okay, and
this other question about are we somehow more
assume that it's easier to,
or let me say it again, that the טומאה וטהרה Tumah VeTahara
is a weightier area than יין נסך Yayin Nesach and we're more
prepared to say there's a טומאה וטהרה Tumah VeTahara problem than a
יין נסך Yayin Nesach problem. That's at least what רב Rav said.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan did not agree to that, but for רב,
Rav, if something is okay from טומאה וטהרה Tumah VeTahara concerns, it's
certainly going to be okay for יין נסך Yayin Nesach concerns. So
those were fascinating comparisons. But bottom line, the upshot of all of
this, as Gloria said, is you get from the case of our
משנה Mishnah where there are limited cases where we are okay and
there are cases even with sealed barrels which are going to be
not good, to a whole range of cases of open barrels and
somebody with froth in their hands and all these various types of
cases where we're much more prepared to say come up with explanations
about why we're assuming that no problem happened. One of them being
this idea of ספק ביאה, Safek Bi'ah, which is like this double
doubt, you know, maybe it was a Jew, maybe it was a
non-Jew, even if it was a non-Jew, maybe they were looking for
money, they weren't looking for wine, etc., etc. Okay, but two key
principles to leave with, again, is this about איצטלי לאישתמוטי Iztali Le-ishtamutei
and נתפס כגנב. Nitpas Ke-ganav. If somebody if they're caught is going
to get in trouble, then we say that we assume that they
did not do anything wrong because they don't want to get in
trouble. That's the key of נתפס כגנב Nitpas Ke-ganav and that's probably
what's been the key in our משנה Mishnah when you leave and
the non-Jew's afraid that you could come back at any moment, and
if you came back at any moment he'd be in trouble, that's
the נתפס כגנב. Nitpas Ke-ganav. Okay, and a related issue was this
איצטלי לאישתמוטי. Iztali Le-ishtamutei. With נתפס כגנב Nitpas Ke-ganav he has a
right to be there, will he get in trouble if he's caught
with his hand in the till, his hand in the wine? איצטלי
לאישתמוטי Iztali Le-ishtamutei is he doesn't have a right to be there
and again, opposite the way I was saying it earlier,
it's a little the reverse of what you would have expected. If
he's got an excuse to be there, then it's more of a
problem, then he feels more secure and he doesn't feel rushed. If
he doesn't have an excuse to be there and he's there anyway,
so while you could think that the issue there is that that's
an evidence that he's up to not good, then we say that
he's feeling rushed and anxious and whatever, and therefore you're actually less
concerned that he handled the wine. Okay, so let's just read, I
know it's already 8:30, but I want to just read this next
משנה Mishnah because it really is just it's a tiny little piece
and it just ends the earlier discussion. Question? Yeah.
Do those two principles show up any place else other than in
this, you know, other than by יין?
Yayin? Well, we had נתפס כגנב Nitpas Ke-ganav applied by טומאה וטהרה
Tumah VeTahara just here, right? That was exactly this case about the
adjoining yards. Whether it applies elsewhere,
I don't know. It's a good question. I mean, I assume you
could imagine it applying in general כשרות Kashrut areas, in supervision areas,
because a lot of what we're learning נכנס ויוצא Nichnas Ve-yotzei and
all those types of things are principles that are used for general
issues of כשרות Kashrut supervision.
But normally כשרות Kashrut supervision, the guy's got a right to be
there and you want to make sure that they're doing the right
thing, that they're following the guidelines you set. Here the point is
that you don't want the guy anywhere in the area and you
know, you don't want them there and you don't want them touching
your stuff.
I'd have to take a look. I would not be at all
surprised that they would because they are general sounding principles of when
do we have to be concerned, you know, about certain types of
behavior. So I wouldn't be at all surprised if they do get
applied elsewhere, but I'd have to check. All right, let's just read
the next little piece. בולשת שנכנסה לעיר בשעת שלום. Boleshet she-nichnesah le-ir
bi-sh’at shalom.
So this is like these troops, okay, and you know, they're sort
of and the word בולשת Boleshet means רש״י says it comes from
the word to search out, like they're in they're coming into a
town and they're also like I said confiscating food and you know,
it's in the middle of a battle, okay. So if they come
in at a time of
peace, then חביות פתוחות אסורות סתומות מותרות. Chaviyot petuchot asurot, setumot mutarot.
The open barrels are all forbidden because you assume they opened them
and they helped themselves to the wine, or if they or even
if they were previously open, you figured they helped themselves to the
wine. But the closed wine obviously are okay. בשעת מלחמה, Bi-sh’at milchamah,
if however they're in the middle of they're fighting a battle, okay,
then אלו ואלו מותרות לפי שאין פנאי לנסך. Elu va-elu mutarot lefi
she-ein penai lenasech. They're all permissible because they don't have a chance
לנסך. Lenasech. Now does it mean they don't have a chance לנסך
Lenasech but they do have a chance to drink the wine? I
mean, even if they're running away from the enemy, אדרבה, Addirabbah, they're
running away from the enemy, they're exhausted, they're thirsty, they're hungry, they'll
help themselves to wine if they see it. So it would be
fascinating if the meaning of this were, even if we're concerned that
they might have drunk the wine, it's not a problem because not
focusing on doing ניסוך. nisuch. That would create a situation in which
a non-Jew could handle wine, but not in a context where we
just say their mind. I mean we had that a little bit
in the previous פרק, perek, right? Where they handled it and it
was incidental and they didn't mean to handle and we say it
wasn't done in a ניסוך nisuch type of a context. That's a
little like the משנה Mishnah sounds like. It sounds like even if
we think they drank the wine, they're too distracted to do ניסוך
nisuch and the wine remains okay. That would be really interesting, especially
if we're saying it was okay even to drink, let alone to,
you know, not just to get הנאה. hana'ah. Let's take a look
at the
גמרא. Gemara רמינהי, Reminehi, I'll ask you on this: עיר שכבשוה כרכום,
ir she-ke-vashua karkum, if a city has been surrounded by a siege,
it's been laid in siege, כל הכהנות שבתוכה פסולות. kol ha-kohannot she-be-tochah
pesulot. You have to assume that the non-Jews who are besieging the
city, when they entered into are entering into the city and they're
raping the women, and therefore all of the wives of כהנים kohanim
are forbidden, because even if it was a rape, the wife of
a כהן kohen who had sex with a non-Jew even through an
act of rape is forbidden. So you see that here it's in
the middle of a war, okay, and even though it's in the
middle of a war, presumably they are finding enough time to rape
the women. Okay, so the גמרא says: אמר רב מרי לנסך אין
פנאי לבעול יש פנאי, Amar Rav Mari: Lenasech ein pnai, livol yesh
pnai, which is lovely, I guess a lovely thing to end on.
Okay, they're too distracted to do עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but for
sex, you know, for rape, I mean, not exactly sex, whatever, rape,
everybody, you know, if you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י says: לנסך
אין פנאי דיצר הניסוך לא תקיף להו וטרודי במלחמה. Lenasech ein pnai
d-yeitzer ha-nisuch lo takif lehu v-trudei b-milchamah. They're too busy fighting the
war to take out time to do a little libation to their
gods. לבעול יש פנאי דתקיף להו יצרייהו, Livol yesh pnai d-takif lehu
yitzraihu, there there's a more powerful urge, you know, which all of
this I find is quite is very whatever disturbing/fascinating. Like, you know,
if they're whatever, if they're in the middle of of raping, if
they've actually conquered the city and therefore they're raping the women, then
they've got time to do the ניסוך nisuch as well. And if
they haven't conquered the city, are they raping the women before they've
conquered the city? So anyway, I don't really get a lot of
this, but but it is quite fascinating in terms of the in
terms of the sort of assumptions that it's making and particularly as
far as our issue about the wine assumption is, is it basically
saying that what do you call it? That even if that even
if they definitely touched it, it's not a problem if we assume
that they didn't do ניסוך. nisuch. It seems to be what's being
said.